Howard A. Seckerson Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Howard A. Seckerson Papers.
undated, 1921-1961.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Seckerson, Howard A.
1.5 linear feet.
Seckerson became head of the English Department at Connecticut Agricultural College in 1921. His development of the department assisted in the conversion from a vocational college into a state university in 1939. His management of the dramatic club laid the foundation for the future Department of Speech and Drama. In addition to teaching, Mr. Seckerson was an ordained minister and returned to pastoral duties after retiring from the University in 1946. At the time of his retirement, the English Department was the largest department on the UConn campus.
MSS19900043
Biography
Howard A. Seckerson was born 3 May 1877 in Brooklyn, NY. He attended Wesleyan University (A.B., 1907) and Yale University (M.A.). His teaching experience, prior to coming to C.A.C. included one year as head of the English Department at Miami Military Institute (Germantown, OH), eight years as department head at Lynchburg High School (Lynchburg, VA) and one year as an English instructor at the University of Texas at Austin. In 1921, Seckerson was offered the position of Department Head at C.A.C. His development of the department assisted in the conversion of the institution from a vocational college into a state university. His management of the dramatic club laid the foundation for the future Department of Speech and Drama. In addition to teaching, Mr. Seckerson was an ordained minister and returned to pastoral duties after retiring from the University. At the tie of his retirement on 14 August 1946, the English Department was the largest department on the UConn campus.
Howard Seckerson married Unade Barnes (22 May 1884, Middletown, CT) at graduate of Wesleyan University (A.B., 1908). She was also an instructor at Connecticut Agricultural College, teaching German and English. The Seckersons had one daughter, Elizabeth.
Howard Seckerson died on 1 March 1970 at the age of 92.
Scope and Content
The Seckerson Papers contain personal correspondence, clippings and campus related memorabilia, as well as academic lecture notes and class preparations.
Arrangement
Series I: Personal Papers ( 1921-1961 ) contains personal correspondence with colleagues, former students and friends. Some of the correspondence concerns the change of name from Connecticut Agricultural College to Connecticut State College (1933) and then to the University of Connecticut (1939). Also included are a campus songbook (1940), campus publications, newspaper clippings, reports and speeches. The series is arranged alphabetically.
Series II: Teaching Materials ( undated ) contains lecture notes and class aids for English courses taught by Seckerson at the one and two hundred levels. The series is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Subjects:
University of Connecticut—Faculty—Professional and personal papers. English language—Study and teaching (Higher)—Connecticut.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; School Records.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Photocopies.; Notes.
Occupations:
Educator.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The Seckerson papers were donated by Mrs. Seckerson in 1970. Additional materials were donated by Elizabeth Seckerson McKain in May 1990.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Personal Papers, undated, 1921-1961
  - Act changing the name of C.A.C., [1933] (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Analysis of first semester registration, 1932 October 1 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Assignment of English classes, 1922-1923 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Babbidge, Homer D., undated (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Baccalaureate degree statement, undated (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Bartman, Julia H., 1940 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Beach, Charles L. (President), 1921-1926 (Box 1:, Folder 7-8)
  - Board of Trustees, undated (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Bonham, H.S., 1921 September 29 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Brezina, Elizabeth S., 1935 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Butterfield, E.W., 1931 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Campus songbook, 1940 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Carleton, P.D., 1936 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Cheney, Maurice L., M.D., 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Christmas and the drama: speech, 1934 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - College Players, 1924 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - College of Storrs, 1931 November 17 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - Collier, Paul D., 1934 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Committee on Curricula and Courses, undated (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Connecticut Campus: article, 1934 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - Connelly, Herbert L., 1925 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Cooper, J.R., 1931 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - The Country Theatre: article, 1924 November (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - Cross, Wilbur L. (Governor), undated (Box 1:, Folder 25)
  - Dahl, Eleanor, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
  - Denlinger, Henry K., 1926 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
  - Department of English faculty, 1935-1946 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
  - Dodge, Richard E., 1934 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
  - Eaton, Edwin Choate, 1928 (Box 1:, Folder 30)
  - Eaton, Wilson, 1945 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
  - Essentials of poetry: address, 1929 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - Faculty of the College: letter, undated (Box 1:, Folder 33)
  - Fellow students: letter, 1931 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - Fraser, Marion, undated (Box 1:, Folder 35)
  - Frost, Edward M., 1920 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
  - Frost, Robert, 1932 (Box 1:, Folder 37)
  - Gentry, Charles B. (Dean), 1940-1945 (Box 1:, Folder 38)
  - Grange: letter, 1932 (Box 1:, Folder 39)
  - Hammond, H. Pierson, 1934 (Box 1:, Folder 40)
  - Hartford Courant: letter, undated (Box 1:, Folder 41)
  - Hawkes, William E., 1942 (Box 1:, Folder 42)
  - Health and Company Nurseries, 1941 (Box 1:, Folder 43)
  - Hutcheson, Harold, 1941 (Box 1:, Folder 44)
  - Institutional name change documents, undated (Box 1:, Folder 45)
  - Jorgenson, Albert N. (President), 1935-1943 (Box 1:, Folder 46-47)
  - Kessel, Marcel, 1934, 1936 (Box 1:, Folder 48)
  - Kuleske, A.L., 1945 (Box 1:, Folder 49)
  - Land grant colleges and universities, 1929 (Box 1:, Folder 50)
  - Leisner, August, 1933 (Box 1:, Folder 51)
  - Little Country Theatre Movement, undated (Box 1:, Folder 52)
  - The Little Theatre: article, undated (Box 1:, Folder 53)
  - Little Theatre Movement: article draft, 1926 (Box 1:, Folder 54)
  - Longley, Raymond (Comptroller), undated (Box 1:, Folder 55)
  - Lowes, John L., 1936 (Box 1:, Folder 56)
  - McCracken, Charles C. (President), 1932-1933 (Box 1:, Folder 57)
  - Memorandum of conference, 1931 September 3 (Box 1:, Folder 58)
  - Newton, H.D.: tribute, 1945 (Box 1:, Folder 59)
  - Non-Professional Theatre, undated (Box 1:, Folder 60)
  - Office of the Provost, 1953-1961 (Box 1:, Folder 61)
  - “Play and the Audience”: paper, undated (Box 1:, Folder 62)
  - President and Board of Trustees, 1934 April (Box 1:, Folder 63)
  - Reminiscences, anecdotes, undated (Box 1:, Folder 64)
  - Report to the Dean, undated (Box 1:, Folder 65)
  - Resolutions on the passing of President Beach, 1933 September 15 (Box 1:, Folder 66)
  - Rockel, Henry J., 1936 (Box 1:, Folder 67)
  - Rowland, Wilimina M., 1942 (Box 1:, Folder 68)
  - Saul, George B., 1936 (Box 1:, Folder 69)
  - Secondary school English programs, 1933 (Box 2:, Folder 70)
  - Shaw, Harold I., 1941 (Box 2:, Folder 71)
  - Smith, Duryea, 1933 (Box 2:, Folder 72)
  - Snow, Wilbert, 1934 (Box 2:, Folder 73)
  - State of Connecticut, undated (Box 2:, Folder 74)
  - State of Connecticut: manual of General Assembly, 1933 (Box 2:, Folder 75)
  - Street, Florence M., undated (Box 2:, Folder 76)
  - Student responsibility in play production, undated (Box 2:, Folder 77)
  - Taddonio, A. Rose, 1947-1960 (Box 2:, Folder 78)
  - Tilley, Winthrop, 1936-1943 (Box 2:, Folder 79)
  - Titles and tenure: recommendations, 1931 (Box 2:, Folder 80)
  - UConn name change: clippings, 1930-1933 (Box 2:, Folder 81)
  - Vinton, Annie: condolences, undated (Box 2:, Folder 82)
  - Walker, Aleny R., 1931 (Box 2:, Folder 83)
  - Warnock, Robert, 1936 (Box 2:, Folder 84)
  - Waugh, Albert E. (Dean, Provost), 1945-1961 (Box 2:, Folder 85)
  - White, George, 1934 (Box 2:, Folder 86)
  - Whiting, Mary B., 1935 (Box 2:, Folder 87)
  - Whitney, Edwina: tribute, 1934 June 5 (Box 2:, Folder 88)
  - Yale University Bureau of Appointments, 1921 (Box 2:, Folder 89)
  - Yanosy, A. William, 1939 (Box 2:, Folder 90)
- Series II: Teaching materials, undated
  - English 106 (Box 3)
    - Biography (Box 3:, Folder 91)
    - Death (Box 3:, Folder 92)
    - The Essay (Box 3:, Folder 93)
    - Feeling/poetry (Box 3:, Folder 94)
    - Introduction to the study of poetry (Box 3:, Folder 95)
    - Nature lyrics (Box 3:, Folder 96)
    - The Novel (Box 3:, Folder 97)
    - Romances (Box 3:, Folder 98)
    - Short story (Box 3:, Folder 99)
    - The Sonnet (Box 3:, Folder 100)
    - Traditional ballad (Box 3:, Folder 101)
    - What is literature (Box 3:, Folder 102)
  - English 124
    - Ancient and Elizabethan theatre (Box 3:, Folder 103)
    - The Classical theatre (Box 3:, Folder 104)
    - Elizabethan and Stuart drama (Box 3:, Folder 105)
    - Four types of plays (Box 3:, Folder 106)
    - The Greek theatre (Box 3:, Folder 107)
    - Interlude (Box 3:, Folder 108)
    - Medieval theatre (Box 3:, Folder 109)
    - Outline of final lecture (Box 3:, Folder 110)
    - Passing of the ancient theatre (Box 3:, Folder 111)
    - Roman theatre (Box 3:, Folder 112)
    - Theatre as religion (Box 3:, Folder 113)
    - Theatres of England (Box 3:, Folder 114)
    - Topics on Shakespeare and the Elizabethan Age (Box 3:, Folder 115)
    - Use of the body: prose and movement (Box 3:, Folder 116)
    - War and the theatre in America (Box 3:, Folder 117)
  - English 209
    - Tennyson and Browning
      - Browning notes (Box 3:, Folder 118)
      - Browning, Elizabeth Barrett (Box 3:, Folder 119)
      - Browning's poetical creed (Box 3:, Folder 120)
      - Tennyson (Box 3:, Folder 121-125)
    - Victorian Literature
      - Arnold, Matthew (Box 3:, Folder 126-128)
      - Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861 (Box 3:, Folder 129)
      - Browning, Robert, 1812-1889 (Box 3:, Folder 130)
      - Clough, Arthur Hugh, 1819-1861 (Box 3:, Folder 131)
      - History of English literature: questions (Box 3:, Folder 132)
      - Lecture notes (Box 3:, Folder 133)
      - Pre-Raphaelites: notes (Box 3:, Folder 134)
      - Tennyson and the Arthurian story (Box 3:, Folder 135)
      - “The Two Voices” (Box 3:, Folder 136)
      - Victorian Age in literature (Box 3:, Folder 137)
      - Victorian notes (Box 3:, Folder 138)
      - Victorian poetry (Box 3:, Folder 139)
      - Warren, John Burn Leicester, 1835-1895 (Box 3:, Folder 140)